window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Discrete_Mathematics — Slot 28 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Discrete_Mathematics — Slot 28",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(\\left(Z, *\\right)\\) be an algebraic structure where Z is the set of integers and the operation * is defined by \\(n*m = \\max(n,m)\\). Which of the following statements is true for \\(\\left(Z, *\\right)\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left(Z, *\\right)\\) is a monoid</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(Z, *\\right)\\) is an Abelian group</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(Z, *\\right)\\) is a group</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2232/gate1997-3-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>The probability that it will rain today is 0.5. The probability that it will rain tomorrow is 0.6. The probability that it will rain either today or tomorrow is 0.7. What is the probability that it will rain today and tomorrow? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0.25</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0.35</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0.4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>0.4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2217/gate1997-1-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The probability that top and bottom cards of a randomly shuffled deck are both aces is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{4}{52} \\times \\frac{4}{52}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{4}{52} \\times \\frac{3}{52}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{4}{52} \\times \\frac{3}{51}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{4}{52} \\times \\frac{4}{51}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{4}{52} \\times \\frac{3}{51}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2736/gate1996-2-7\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is false? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The set of all bijective functions on a finite set forms a group under function composition.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The set \\(\\{1, 2, \\dots p-1\\}\\) forms a group under multiplication mod p, where p is a prime number.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The set of all strings over a finite alphabet forms a group under concatenation.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>A subset \\(S \\neq \\emptyset\\) of G is a subgroup of the group \\(\\langle G, * \\rangle\\)  if and only if for any pair of elements \\(a, b \\in S, a * b^{-1} \\in S\\).</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>The set of all strings over a finite alphabet forms a group under concatenation.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2733/gate1996-2-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is false? Read \\(\\wedge\\) as AND, \\(\\vee\\) as OR, \\(\\neg\\) as NOT,  \\(\\rightarrow\\) as one way implication and \\(\\leftrightarrow\\) as two way implication <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(((x \\rightarrow y) \\wedge x) \\rightarrow y\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(((\\neg x \\rightarrow y) \\wedge (\\neg x \\rightarrow \\neg y)) \\rightarrow x\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((x \\rightarrow (x \\vee y))\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(((x \\vee y) \\leftrightarrow (\\neg x \\rightarrow \\neg y))\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(((x \\vee y) \\leftrightarrow (\\neg x \\rightarrow \\neg y))\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2732/gate1996-2-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Let R be a non-empty relation on a collection of sets defined by \\(_{A}R_ B\\) if and only if \\(A \\cap B = \\phi\\). Then, (pick the true statement) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A is reflexive and transitive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R is symmetric and not transitive</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R is an equivalence relation</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R is not reflexive and not symmetric</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>R is symmetric and not transitive</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2731/gate1996-2-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Let R denote the set of real numbers. Let \\(f:R\\times R \\rightarrow R \\times R\\) be a bijective function defined by \\(f(x,y) = (x+y, x-y)\\). The inverse function of \\(f\\) is given by <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f^{-1} (x,y) = \\left( \\frac {1}{x+y}, \\frac{1}{x-y}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(f^{ -1} (x,y) = (x-y , x+y)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(f^{-1} (x,y) = \\left( \\frac {x+y}{2}, \\frac{x-y}{2}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(f^{-1}(x,y)=\\left [ 2\\left(x-y\\right),2\\left(x+y\\right) \\right ]\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(f^{-1} (x,y) = \\left( \\frac {x+y}{2}, \\frac{x-y}{2}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2730/gate1996-2-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Two dice are thrown simultaneously. The probability that at least one of them will have 6 facing up is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{36}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{25}{36}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{11}{36}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{11}{36}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2709/gate1996-1-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements is FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The set of rational numbers is an abelian group under addition</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The set of integers in an abelian group under addition</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The set of rational numbers form an abelian group under multiplication</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The set of real numbers excluding zero is an abelian group under multiplication</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>The set of rational numbers form an abelian group under multiplication</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2708/gate1996-1-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Suppose X and Y are sets and |X| and |Y| are their respective cardinality. It is given that there are exactly 97 functions from X to Y. From this one can conclude that <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>|X| =1, |Y| =97</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>|X| =97, |Y| =1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>|X| =97, |Y| =97</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>|X| =1, |Y| =97</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2707/gate1996-1-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(X = \\{2, 3, 6, 12, 24\\}\\), Let \\(\\leq\\) be the partial order defined by \\(X \\leq Y\\) if x divides y. Number of edges in the Hasse diagram of \\((X, \\leq)\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>9</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2706/gate1996-1-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Let A and B be sets and let \\(A^c\\) and \\(B^c\\) denote the complements of the sets A and B. The set \\((A-B) \\cup (B-A) \\cup (A \\cap B)\\) is equal to <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(A \\cup B\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(A^c \\cup B^c\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(A \\cap B\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(A^c \\cap B^c\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(A \\cup B\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2705/gate1996-1-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>If the proposition \\(\\lnot p \\to q\\) is true, then the truth value of the proposition \\(\\lnot p \\lor \\left ( p \\to q \\right )\\), where \\(\\lnot\\) is negation, \\(\\lor\\) is inclusive OR and \\(\\to\\) is implication, is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>TRUE</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Multiple Values</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>FALSE</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Cannot be determined</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Cannot be determined</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2631/gate1995-2-19\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Let A be the set of all non-singular matrices over real number and let * be the matrix multiplication operation. Then <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A is closed under * but \\(\\langle A, *\\rangle\\) is not a semigroup.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\langle A, *\\rangle\\) is a semigroup but not a monoid.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\langle A, *\\rangle\\) is a monoid but not a group.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\langle A, *\\rangle\\) is a a group but not an abelian group.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\langle A, *\\rangle\\) is a a group but not an abelian group.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2629/gate1995-2-17\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>A bag contains 10 white balls and 15 black balls. Two balls are drawn in succession. The probability that one of them is black and the other is white is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{2}{3}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{4}{5}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2626/gate1995-2-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
